Fabio Miranda

University of Illinois at Chicago

851 S. Morgan St, MC 152, Chicago, IL, 60607

□ (+1) 347-545-6405 | **S** fabiom@uic.edu | **A** fmiranda.me

Research Interests

I am interested in developing techniques that allow for the interactive visual analysis of large-scale data, combining methods from visualization, data management, machine learning and computer graphics. I have worked closely with domain experts from different fields and the outcome of these collaborations included not only research published in leading venues, but also systems that were made available to experts in academia, industry and government agencies. My work has also received extensive coverage from different media outlets, including The New York Times, The Economist, Architectural Digest, Curbed, among others.

Education

2012 - 2018 Ph.D. in Computer Science New York, NY, USA

New York University (NYU) Advised by Cláudio T. Silva.

Dissertation: "Data structures for the interactive visual analysis of urban data".

2009 - 2011 M.S. in Computer Science Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil

Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio)

Advised by Waldemar Celes.

Thesis: "Volume rendering of unstructured hexahedral meshes".

2005 - 2009 **B.S. in Computer Science** Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Advised by Luiz Chaimowicz.

Professional Experience

Fall 2020 - present **University of Illinois at Chicago** Chicago, IL, USA

Assistant Professor

New York University Fall 2018 - Fall 2020

New York, NY, USA

Postdoctoral researcher

Development of new techniques for the interactive visualization of different types of large-scale data, such as streaming timeseries data and image data. Also responsible for mentoring PhD students.

Summer 2016 **Argonne National Laboratory** Lemont, IL, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Venkatram Vishwanath

Developed a visualization tool to explore high-resolution volumetric weather simulations, focused in the Chicago metropolitan area, in order to understand the impact of built environment on the city climate.

IBM T.J. Watson Research Center Summer 2015

Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Bruce D'Amora

Developed a web-based graph visualization tool for the exploratory visualization of bitcoin transactions.

Summer 2014 AT&T Research

Middletown, NJ, USA

Research intern

Mentors: Lauro Lins and James Klosowski

Developed a distributed version of Nanocubes, a datacube-based approach for the visualization of massive spatiotemporal datasets.

FABIO MIRANDA · CURRICULUM VITAE

Summer 2013 Sandia National Laboratories Albuquerque, NM, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Patricia Crossno

Developed an adaptive kernel density estimation approach for scatterplots using GPUs.

2009 - 2012 **TecGraf / PUC-Rio**

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Research assistant Mentor: Waldemar Celes

Developed an unstructured hexahedral volume renderer for a data visualization and analysis software

used in most of Brazil's oil fields.

Awards

2018 SIGMOD Best Demonstration Award

For "Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets Using Urbane".

2018 Pearl Brownstein Doctoral Research Award

For doctoral research that shows the greatest promise, awarded by NYU.

2010-2012 CAPES and Petrobras Fellowships

Awarded during M.S. studies.

2006-2009 FINEP and CNPq Fellowships

Awarded during B.S. studies.

Selected Media Coverage

September 2017 Urban Pulse Uses Social Media Data to Show Cities in a New Light

Architectural Digest 🗗

September 2017 New program wants to improve cities with the power of tweets and Flickr uploads

Curbed 2

2019

December 2016 Mapping the Shadows of New York City: Every Building, Every Block

The New York Times 🗷

October 2016 Listen to the music of the traffic in the city

The Economist 🗷

Publications

Urban Mosaic: Visual Exploration of Streetscapes Using Large-scale Image Data

F. Miranda, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, M. Hosseini, G. Dove, C. T. Silva

2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

Learning Geo-Contextual Embeddings for Commuting Flow Prediction

Z. Liu, F. Miranda, W. Xiong, J. Yang, Q. Wang, C. T. Silva

Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence.

Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale Shadows over Time

F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 25, no. 3, pp. 1559-1574, Mar 2019.

Featured on The New York Times

Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual Analysis of Large Time Series

F. Miranda, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Mydlarz, J. Salamon, Y. Lockerman, J. Freire, C. T. Silva

Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 37, no. 3, pp. 23-35, Jun 2018.

Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets using Urbane H. Doraiswamy, E. Tzirita Zacharatou, **F. Miranda**, M. Lage, A. Ailamaki, C. T. Silva, J. Freire 2018 ACM SIGMOD Intl. Conf. on Management of Data - Demo.

Best Demonstration Award

Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Analysis: A Visual Analytics Perspective

H. Doraiswamy, J. Freire, M. Lage, F. Miranda, C. T. Silva

IEEE Computer Graphics and Application, vol. 38, no. 5, pp. 26-35, Sept/Oct 2018.

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 1394-1407, Mar 2018.

2017 Urban Pulse: Capturing the Rhythm of Cities

F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, K. Zao, B. Goncalves, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 23, no. 1, pp. 791-800, Jan 2017.* Featured on The Economist, invited to SIGGRAPH 2017 TVCG special session

Data Visualization Tool for Monitoring Transit Operation and Performance

A. Kurkcu, F. Miranda, K. Ozbay, C. T. Silva

5th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Models and Technologies for Intelligent Transportation Systems (2017).

2016 TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

Data Systems for Interactive Analysis (DSIA) 2016.

Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes

F. Miranda, and W. Celes

The Visual Computer Journal, vol. 28, no. 10, pp. 1005-1014, Oct 2012.

Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes

F. Miranda, and W. Celes

24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).

Illustrative Volume Visualization for Unstructured Meshes Based on Photic Extremum Lines

A. Rocha, F. Miranda, and W. Celes

24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).

Teaching Experience

Fall 2019 CS GY 6533: Interactive Computer Graphics

New York University

Graduate course. Prepared and presented 2.5 hour lecture on shadows.

Fall 2014 CS UY 1133: Data Structures and Algorithms

New York University

Undergraduate course. Prepared and presented 2.5 hour lecture on C and C++ programming.

Fall 2014 CUSP GX 5003: Principles of Urban Informatics

New York University

Teaching assistant for Cláudio T. Silva, 50 students

Graduate course. Prepared and presented lectures on visualization, python, pandas and MySQL. Created and graded assignments, and held office hours.

Fall 2013 CUSP GX 5003: Principles of Urban Informatics

New York University

Teaching assistant for Cláudio T. Silva, 50 students

Graduate course. Developed and presented lectures on visualization, python, javascript, D3 and MySQL. Prepared and graded assignments, and held office hours.

Mentoring Experience

2018 - Mentor Ph.D. Students

New York University

Mentor students to work with the Urbane framework, as well as on research projects.

Students: Zhicheng Liu (CS PhD student at Southeast University, China), Maryam Hosseini (Urban Systems PhD student at Rutgers), Shaoyu Chen (CS PhD student at NYU), João Rulff (CS PhD student at NYU).

Invited Talks and Presentations

February 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights University of Illinois at Chicago	Chicago, CA, USA
February 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights Illinois Institute of Technology	Chicago, IL, USA
February 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights San Diego State University	San Diego, CA, USA
February 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights Tulane University	New Orleans, LA, USA
February 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights The University of New Orleans	New Orleans, LA, USA
January 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights Portland State University	Portland, OR, USA
January 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights Virginia Commonwealth University	Richmond, VA, USA
January 2020	Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable Insights University of Massachusetts - Dartmouth	Dartmouth, MA, USA
December 2018	Exploration of Street-Level Images at Scale Pedestrian Movement Technology Showcase at Metro North	New York City, NY, USA
November 2018	Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale Shadows over Time IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)	Berlin, Germany
June 2018	Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual Analysis of Large Time Series EG/VGTC Conference on Visualization (EuroVis)	Brno, Czech Republic
October 2017	TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS)	Phoenix, AZ, USA
September 2016	Visualizing and Exploring Urban Data Data Visualization Summit	Boston, MA, USA

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of
Spatiotemporal Datasets

Data Systems for Interactive Analysis Workshop (DSIA)

October 2011 Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes Maceió, Brazil
Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images

Selected Open-Source Projects

New York City Shadow Data
Shadow data for New York City, also used by The New York Times.

2018 Urban PulseOpen-source version of Urban Pulse paper.

Open-source tool for the exploration of a large data set with bus tracking pings. Developed in close collaboration with the New York City Department of Transportation.

Service

Bus Explorer

2017

Program Committees: IEEE VIS 2020 Short papers, Sibgrapi 2020, IEEE VIS 2019 Short papers, Sibgrapi 2019. Reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Big Data, IEEE InfoVis, IEEE SciVis, IEEE VAST, Sibgrapi, WWW, The Visual Computer Journal, Transportation Research Record Journal, International Conference on Pattern Recognition.